A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Secretary of Transportation, 2014-2018
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of the Virginia Secretary of Transportation, 2014-2018
The Library of Virginia
52182
5.85 cubic feet (13 Boxes)
Virginia Secretary of Transportation
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from the Virginia Secretary of Transportation on 10 January 2018.
Historical Information
In 1970, the Governor's Management Commission Study recommended the creation of six "Deputy Governors" to assist the Chief Executive in his managerial duties. Compatible functions of government were grouped under these administrative heads, who would serve as the Governors top management team or "secretariats," as they are called now.
Governor Linwood Holton's top priority for the 1972 session of the General Assembly was a proposal for a Governor's Cabinet, reorganizing state agencies into six major departments--each headed by a secretary appointed by the governor. Transportation and public safety was one of these six departments. The office of Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety was created on April 8, 1972, by an act passed by the General Assembly. Governor Holton appointed Wayne A. Whitham, a member of the Winchester City Council, as the first Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety. When Whitham took office on July 1, 1972, he was responsible for State Highway Commission, Division of Motor Vehicles, Department of State Police, Highway Safety Division, Office of Emergency Services, Department of Military Affairs, Virginia State Crime Commission and the Law Enforcement Officers Training Standards Commission. The Office has undergone a series of administrative reorganizations since. On April 12, 1976, the Legislature established separate secretariats for transportation and for public safety, effective July 1, 1976. On July 1, 1984, the offices were again combined. Most recently, the Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety was divided into separate secretariats on February 22, 1990. The Secretary of Transportation is a member of the Governor's Cabinet, and is appointed by the governor, subject to confirmation by the General Assembly. The Secretary is responsible to the governor for the Department of Transportation, Department of Rail and Public Transportation, Department of Aviation, Department of Motor Vehicles, Virginia Port Authority and the Motor Vehicle Dealers Board.
Aubrey Layne, Jr., was reappointed Virginia's Secretary of Transportation by Governor Terrence McAuliffe on 22 November 2013. Layne was appointed the Commonwealth Transportation Board as the Hampton Roads representative in 2009 and to the Chesapeake Bay Bridge Tunnel Commission in 2010. Prior to his appointment, Layne served as President of the Achievable Dream Academies and before that as President and Principal Broker of Great Atlantic Properties. Layne earned a B.A. in Accounting from the University of Richmond is 1979, is a Certified Public Accountant, and received an MBA from Old Dominion University in 1997.
Scope and Content
The Secretary of Transportation records, 2014-2018, consist of 13 archival boxes and are divided into 4 series. Series have been designated for Correspondence - Assigned State Agencies (I), Correspondence - Secretary (II), Decision briefs (III) and Subject files (IV). These records document the work of Secretary of Transportation Aubrey Layne, Jr., during the McAuliffe administration and were created or collected, 2014-2018, though some documents in this collection pre-date this time period.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Correspondence - Assigned State Agencies, 2014-201 8(bulk 2014-2017)
Series II. Correspondence - Secretary, 2014-2017
Series III. Decision memoranda, 2014-2018 (buk 2014-2017)
Series IV. Subject files, 2014-2017
Contents List
- Series I. Correspondence - Assigned State Agencies, 2014-2018 (bulk 2014-2017)., Extent: 9 boxes. (Box 1-9)
  Correspondence - Assigned State Agencies, 2014-2018, is housed in 9 archival box and is arranged chronologically within each agency. This series consists primarily of incoming correspondence and related attachments from local, state and federal government officials, state and federal legislators, officials from other states, business owners, and associations, as well as constituent correspondence that was sent either directly to the Secretary of Transporation or sent to the Governor and referred to the Secretary. Correspondence was accordingly forwarded to specific agencies for response based on topic. Also includes correspondence between the Secretary and agencies, as well as a few copies of outgoing correspondence. Attachments may include agreements, articles, budgets, invitations, legislation, memorandums of understanding, presentations, and reports. Topics include environmental health, health insurance, legislation, lyme disease, Medicaid, mental health facilities, and social services, among others. Includes correspondence with the following agencies: Dept. of Aviation (DOAV), Dept. of Motor Vehicles (DMV), Dept. of Rail and Public Transportation (DRPT), Dept. of Transportation (VDOT), and the Virginia Port Authority (VPA).
  Topics for DOAV may include, but are not limited to: aerospace, airline service, airports, Federal Aviation Authority, policies, funding, Metropolitan Washington Airports Authority, state aircraft, Virginia Airport Operators Council, and the Washington Airports Task Force.
  Topics for DMV may include, but are not limited to: Driver's licenses, funding, legislation, REAL ID, taxis/uber, and transportation safety grants.
  Topics for DRPT may include, but are not limited to: Bus transportation, CSX projects, Federal Transit Administration, federal and state transportation funding, grants, high speed rail, Metropolitan Washington Airports Authority, policies and procedures, railroads, and safety.
  Topics for VDOT may include, but are not limited to: Budget, Commonwealth Transportation Board, EZ Pass / tolling policies, Federal Highway Administration, Hampton Roads Transportation Planning Organization, HB2 Prioritizarion Project, interstate congestion, local traffic issues, Northern Virginia Transportation Authority, Public Private Transportation Act (PPTA), regional transportation priorities, revenue bonds, Statewide Transportation Improvement Program / Six Year Improvement Program, Washington Airports Task Force, Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority, and transportaion construction projects including the I-95 corridor, I-66 corridor, Route 460, and Route 29 western bypass.
  Topics for VPA may include, but are not limited to: Economic growth, Newport News Shipbuiling, Port of Richmond, shipbuilding, and the Virginia International Gateway Terminal.
  - Virginia Dept. of Aviation (DOAV), 2014-2017.
    - Correspondence, 2014-2015. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 2014 May. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 2016-2017. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Metropolitan Washington Airports Authority - Annual Financial Report (2016), 2017. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Virginia Dept. of Motor Vehicles (DMV). 2014-2017.
    - Correspondence, 2014 Jan-June. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 2014 July-Dec. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 2015. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 2016. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, 2017. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Virginia Dept. of Rail and Public Transportation (DRPT), 2014-2017.
    - Correspondence, 2014 Jan-Apr. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 2014 May-Aug. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 2014 Sept-Dec. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 2015 Jan-June. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 2015 Sept-Dec. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 2016 Jan-June. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 2016 July-Dec. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 2017 Feb-Sept. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, 2017 Dec. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Title VI Plan, 2016 Feb 29. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Virginia Port Authority (VPA), 2014-2017.
    - Correspondence, 2014-2017. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Infrastructure funding request, 2015 Nov. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Virginia Dept. of Transportation (VDOT), 2014-2018 (bulk 2014-2017).
    - Correspondence, 2014 Jan 1-18. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 2014 Jan 20-31. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 2014 Feb. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 2014 Mar. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 2014 Apr. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 2014 May. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 2014 June 4-9. (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 2014 June 10. (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, 2014 June 11-25. (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, 2014 July. (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, 2014 Aug. (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, 2014 Sept. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 2014 Oct 1-17. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 2014 Oct 20-30. (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 2014 Nov. (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence - Revenue bonds, 2014 Nov 19. (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 2014 Dec. (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 2015 Jan. (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 2015 Feb. (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, 2015 Mar. (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 2015 Apr. (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 2015 May 1-18. (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 2015 May 19-29. (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 2015 June 2-15. (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 2015 June 16-30. (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 2015 July. (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 2015 July. (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, 2015 Aug. (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, 2015 Sept. (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, 2015 Oct 1-19. (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 2015 Oct 20-30. (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 2015 Nov. (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 2015 Dec 1-19. (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 2015 Dec 20-30. (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 2016 Jan 1-10. (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 2016 Jan 11-19. (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 2016 Jan 20-30. (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, 2016 Feb 1-11. (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, 2016 Feb 12-29. (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, 2016 Mar 1-10. (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, 2016 Mar 11-31. (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, 2016 Apr 4-12. (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 2016 Apr 14-28. (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 2016 May 2-11. (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 2016 May 12-29. (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 2016 June. (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 2016 July. (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 2016 Aug. (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 2016 Sept 1-23. (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, 2016 Sept 27-30. (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, 2016 Oct. (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, 2016 Nov. (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, 2016 Dec. (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, 2017 Jan. (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 2017 Feb. (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 2017 Mar. (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 2017 Apr. (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 2017 May. (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence - Queenslake Community Association, 2017 May. (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 2017 June. (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 2017 July. (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, 2017 Aug. (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, 2017 Sept. (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 2017 Oct. (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 2017 Nov. (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 2017 Dec. (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 2018 Jan. (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Series II. Correspondence - Secretary, 2014-2017., Extent: 9 folders. (Box 10)
  Correspondence, 2014-2017, is housed in 1 archival box and is arranged chronologically. This series contains primarily incoming correspondence and related attachments from from local, state and federal government officials, state and federal legislators, officials from other states, and associations, as well as constituent correspondence sent directly to the Secretary of Transportation. Also include monthly support services financial statements. This series is indistinguishable from correspondence with state agencies. Correspondence may include related materials such as presentations and reports. Topics include congratulations, constituent concerns, highway construction projectd, legislation, tolls, and transportation funding.
  - Correspondence, 2014. (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 2015. (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 2016. (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 2017. (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence - Financial statements, 2013. (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence - Financial statements, 2014. (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence - Financial statements, 2015. (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence - Financial statements, 2016. (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence - Financial statements, 2017. (Box 10, Folder 9)
- Series III. Decision briefs, 2014-2018 (bulk 2014-2017)., Extent: .5 cu. ft. (Box 10-11)
  Decision briefs, 2014-2018, are housed in 2 archival boxes and are arranged chronologically. These briefs consist of Governor Decision Requests sent to the Office of Governor McAuliffe and include a cover sheet with a brief description and routing/approval information, as well as attached correspondence. Decision requests cover topics such as aircraft use and policies, appointments, DMV fees, funding, grants, hiring, letters for governor's signature, Port of Virginia, rail transit, REAL ID, regulations, and the Transportation Partnership Opportunity Fund.
  - Decision briefs, 2014 Jan-Mar. (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Decision briefs, 2014 Apr-June. (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Decision briefs, 2014 July-Dec. (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Decision briefs, 2015 Feb-June. (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Decision briefs, 2015 July-Dec. (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Decision briefs, 2016 Feb-Apr. (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Decision briefs, 2016 May-July. (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Decision briefs, 2016 Aug-Dec. (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Decision briefs, 2017 Feb-July. (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Decision briefs, 2017 Aug-Dec. (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Decision briefs, 2018 Jan. (Box 11, Folder 6)
- Series IV. Subject files, 2014-2017., Extent: 1.05 cu. ft. (Box 11-13)
  Subject files, 2014-2017, are housed in 3 archival boxes and are arranged alphabetically. This series includes project and topical files and may contain correspondence, conference materials, notes, presentations and reports.
  - Economic Outlook and Revenue Forecast (through 2020), 2017. (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Metropolitan Washing Airports Authority - Annual Financial Report, 2014-2015. (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous notes, 2014-2017. (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Partnerships Infrastructure and Investment Conference, 2014. (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Six Year Improvement Program (2017-2022) - Draft (Part I), 2016 May 18. (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Six Year Improvement Program (2017-2022) - Draft (Part II), 2016 May 18. (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Six Year Improvement Program (2018-2023) - Final (Part I), 2017 June 20. (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Six Year Improvement Program (2018-2023) - Final (Part II), 2017 June 20. (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Transportation Research Board (TRB), 2015. (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Transform Interstate 66 Project (1 of 6), 2015. (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Transform Interstate 66 Project (2 of 6), 2015. (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Transform Interstate 66 Project (3 of 6), 2015. (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Transform Interstate 66 Project (4 of 6), 2015. (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Transform Interstate 66 Project (5 of 6), 2015. (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Transform Interstate 66 Project (6 of 6), 2015. (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Virginia Commercial Space Flight Authority, 2014-2015. (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Virginia Transportation Infrastructure Bank (VITB), 2010-2012. (Box 13, Folder 9)